[SPEAKER_00]: Dear Venerables, for a long time I felt that I should keep the eight precepts, but I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finding your teachings two weeks ago pushed me to finally take them on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I ended a relationship, shaved my head, put on white clothes, and have been dedicated to non-delight in sleep and food.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm driven by the urgency of not knowing how much time I have left and spend my days in reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But something has shifted.
[SPEAKER_00]: My energy has collapsed into hopelessness and dread.
[SPEAKER_00]: I often find myself in tears during the meals and work periods at the monastery I'm currently visiting, unable to hide it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The people around me don't seem to understand, and I'm starting to wonder if anyone ever could.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I see that a part of myself is yearning to give up these eight precepts and revert back to the five.
[SPEAKER_00]: But something in me has shifted and knows that that path leads nowhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know going back would fix nothing, and yet part of me fears that I will.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I endure this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the difference between you logically understanding what's good for you and then actually feeling that that's what's good for you, so to speak, so that you actually stop wanting the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while the first
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing that you need to get out of the way is to understand that if you act out of that feeling that's still there of desire towards what isn't good for you, then there's no way that that
[SPEAKER_01]: When wrong perception will fade, it will only become stronger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it might even come a point where the strength of that pressure will, like, take over even your now factual recognition of what's good for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be clear about the fact that, okay, whatever I choose, I will not be able to remain static.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like I can stay where I am and sort of resume later.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I choose to go down that path, I will lose what I have built up and I might end up even in an even worse position.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be clear about that, because then it... it... it... that will play a big part in the... in what you choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to, as many people do, maintain the view that you are practicing while you're actually not restrained from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be clear that, actually, I have chosen to go in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, now, in terms of what do you do, if you do choose to keep the eight precepts, well, you have to recognize to what extent you're actually responsible for that
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of gratification and enjoyment of the things that you've given up, that's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to realize that actually you're not doing that anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you said, you yourself have a clear line that you're not crossing, because you started keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that's arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not something that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, you would probably
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important to see then that you shouldn't overreach beyond that point and then try to suppress or or speed up the abandonment of that delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, it's when you
[SPEAKER_01]: Leave it be there, but don't act out of it and don't try to get rid of it, that it will actually start subsiding from the very base where it is, rather than simply suppressing it through like an engagement of you, almost like through sense of willpower, doing this and doing that and striving and contemplating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meanwhile, that thing kind of lingers there at the background and you know that as soon as you
[SPEAKER_01]: Relax and sit down.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to come back and take over.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's not the right type of abandonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only right type of abandonment is when, even if you were to not strive anymore, that desire just isn't there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way you can achieve that is, if you learn how to, well, as we say, endure it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, it certainly doesn't mean that you
[SPEAKER_01]: Allow the fantasizing and memories and thoughts that that state will be trying to push on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to restrain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, you try to keep in check that sense of... Oh, this is... that sense of ownership over it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a right to make this go away on my own terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way as
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't even ask for that state in it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It built up as a result of the stuff that you've been doing in the past, as a as a as a kind of momentum that you have accumulated through your past actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now in the same way, you won't be able to just shift gears immediately into the other direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start building up that momentum, so that then your mind starts actually delighting in renunciation, and then that's the thing that's happening on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you will realize in the same way that now, it feels probably almost impossible to actually not have those unwholesome inclinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you cultivate the opposite type of momentum, it will start feeling impossible to have the unwholesome inclinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will feel like the mind is just on its own, preferring the precepts, preferring renunciation, and the thought of going back is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the end result of you seeing that state of mind as arisen and not interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Satipaṭṭhāna Sūtra describes, you recognize the mind of lust as a mind of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't add on top of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you are recognizing it as a mind of lust, you won't be able to proliferate the thoughts it wants you to proliferate at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to be afraid that if I don't deal with it as soon as possible, that I'll somehow be falling prey to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't fall prey to it if you're recognizing it as an arisen state of mind at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't you recognize it as an arisen state of mind that you don't like and want to get rid of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but the thing is, if you were to start trying to get rid of it, you wouldn't be recognizing it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's also mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you certainly don't want to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a view that it's a good state or something, and that it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't justify... Because, like, factually, you will lose perspective over it, if you start trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, the only way I can really see it, is if I'm not engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same of, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're looking at something from a higher ground,
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to go and wrestle with it and keep that higher ground at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that it might feel unpleasant to have to look at it, but you have to realize, well, as long as I don't go down there, where it is, I'm not gonna get injured.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can't, like, somehow magically hit me from afar.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only when I go and start, for whatever reason, get close to it,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when I get in trouble.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will take time for that to fully sink in, because everything that you've lived so far is about, like, immediately jumping into your states of mind, in whichever direction, to get rid of them or to manipulate them out of that sense of ownership that you still have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, the sense of giving up the sense of ownership doesn't mean that your mind kind of ends up
[SPEAKER_01]: Neglected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not yours anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you cultivate non-ownership, your mind will be purified as a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not something you can do out of a sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't take your ownership for granted and then use it to try to purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ownership is what pollutes the mind.